American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIb. 1807-1825 APS.Archives.IIb APS.Archives.IIb
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - H. Steinhauer to Jno. Vaughan, March 2, 1816; 7 1/2" x 9 1/8"; Steinhauer, H.
    Bethlehem, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Forwards to the A.P.S.: [George Henry] Loskiel, History of the mission of the United Brethren among the Indians in North America.
  - W(illiam) Rawle to (Peter S.) DuPonceau, March 4, 1816; 6 1/2" x 7 7/8"; Rawle, William, 1759-1836
    ----, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Opinion upon a letter of William Penn, sent by Rawle to (John) Vaughan "a few weeks age."
  - Report of Peter S. DuPonceau to [the American Philosophical Society], March 6, 1816; 8 1/16" x 13 5/8"; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.D.S. Recommends the publication of a number of letters and documents relating to William Penn and early Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, March 9, 1816; 10x8; Testard et Gueun L'ainé et cie
    Marseilles, L. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Forwards volumes from Dr. Valentin.
  - Peter S. DuPonceau to John Vaughan, March 11, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Regarding documents of interest to the A.P.S., in possession of Miers Fisher and Deborah Logan.
  - Alex(ander) Graydon to Peter S. DuPonceau, March 12, 1816; 7 7/8" x 10"; Graydon, Alexander, 1752-1818
    Harrisburg, 3 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Lists documents in his possession that might be of interest to the Historical Committee of the A.P.S.
  - N. B. Boileau to Casper [sic) Wistar, March 13, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Boileau, Nathaniel B., 1762?-1850
    President of the A.P.S., Harrisburg, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Transmits to the A.P.S.: Smith's edition of the Laws of Pennsylvania.
  - Report on the memorial relative to the first discovery of the new genus of plants called Bartonia., 1816 March 15; American Philosophical Society.
    Signed by J. Correa de Serra and Zaccheus Collins. Publication not recommended.
  - S(amuel) J. Smith to (Thomas C.) James, March 18, 1816; 8" x 10"; Smith, Samuel J.
    Burlington, (N. J.), 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Will send such historical material as may be found among his father's papers to the Historical Committee of the A.P.S.
  - John Simson to John Vaughan, March 22, 1816; 8" x 9 3/4"; Simson, John
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.N. in 3d. per. Presents to the A.P.S.: a "specimen of the Chinese language."
  - R(edmond) Conyngham to John Vaughan, March 25, 1816; 8" x 9 7/8"; Conyngham, Redmond, 1781-1846
    Lancaster, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Has been working in land office and office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth upon documents of interest to the A.P.S. L-2
  - Notes of an argument respecting the old and new calendar in Pennsylvania, March, 1816; 13-1/2x8; Fisher, Miers, 1748-1819
    [ca.]. D. 4p.and end. This was given to DuPonceau in reply to his letter from the Historical committee to Fisher; March 9, 1816.
  - W(illia)m Graham to Peter S. DuPonceau, April 2, 1816; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Graham, William
    Chester, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Possesses documents relative to the early history of Pennsylvania which he is willing to donate to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Benjamin Harrison and W[illia]m Page, April 3, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 36.) States purpose of the committee and asks aid, especially in the manuscript of the running of the Virginia-N.Carolina boundary by William Byrd. For answer, see letter from Harrison to Mrs.E.C.Izard; April 28, 1816.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, [1816] April 4; Meade, William
    Accompanies the presentation of his work On the origin and progress of galvanism to the A.P.S..
  - H. G. Spafford to P[eter] S. DuPonceau, April 5, 1816; 8 3/8" x 9 7/8"; Spafford, Horatio Gates, 1778-1832
    Albany, 1p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Forwards his paper upon "The Art of Making Iron," to the A.P.S.
  - W[illia]m Graham to Peter S. DuPonceau, April 6, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Graham, William
    Chester, 1 p., address and endorsements. A.L.S. Has packed six volumes, Votes of Provincial Assembly (of Pennsylvania), to be sent to the A.P.S. See: same to same, April 2, 1816.
  - Letter to [Louis Hue] Girardin, Richmond, April 15, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol.1,no.39.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
  - W[illiam] Vaughan to the President of the [American] Philosophical Society, April 18, 1816; 8" x 9 3/4"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London, 1p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Forwards to the A.P.S.: Catalogue of the library of the Antiquarian Society of London.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, 1816 April 23; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831
    Letter introduces Count Regnaud de St. Jean Angeli, who wishes to invesitgate Philadelphia institutions, including the A.P.S. and the Pennsylvania School of Medicine.
  - David Hosack to Peter S. DuPonceau, April 25, 1816; 8" x 9 7/8"; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, 2 pp., address and endorsement. New York Historical Society offers to exchange communications with the Historical Committee of the A.P.S.
  - Ben(jamin) Harrison to Mrs. E.C.Izard, April 28, 1816; 8 1/8" x 9-3/4"; Harrison, Benjamin
    Berkley, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. With regard to William Byrd papers at Westover.
  - Benj(ami)n Harrison to Mrs. (E. C.) Izard, April 28, 1816; 8 1/2" x 12"; Harrison, Benjamin
    Berkley, 1 p. and endorsement. Copy. with regard to the William Byrd papers at Westover.
  - [Timothy] Pitkin to [John] Vaughan, April 30, 1816; 4 15/16" x 7 7/8"; Pitkin, Timothy, 1766-1847
    Washington, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L. in 3d. per. Presents to the A.P.S., his Statistical view of the commerce of the U.S.
  - (Mrs.) E. C. Izard to John Vaughan, May, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Izard, Elizabeth C. (Elizabeth Carter), ca. 1774-1826
    ----, n. d., but ca. late April or early 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Encloses letter from Benjamin Harrison to Mrs. E. C. Izard, April 28, 1816, with regard to the William byrd papers at Westover.
  - Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau, May 4, 1816; 10x8; Graham, John, 1774-1820
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Forwards copy of French manuscript on the history of Louisiana and gives history of it. Refers to Jefferson. For copy, see first pages of: La Harpe Journal… FILM199 FRAME762
  - Tench Coxe to Peter S. DuPonceau, May 7, 1816; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Coxe, Tench, 1755-1824
    State House Square, [Philadelphia], 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents "statement of the manufactures of the United States" to the Historical and Literary Committee of the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Jason Chamberlain, Burlington, May 7, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 42.) Asks for aid in Indian linguistics. Says that Jefferson referred him. FILM199 FRAME 670
  - Peter S. DuPonceau to J[ohn] Vaughan, May 7, 1816; 8 1/4" x 13 3/4"; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. With respect to the arrangement of pamphlets in the A.P.S. library. See: same to same, May 24, 1816.
  - Abiel Holmes to Peter S. DuPonceau, May 8, 1816; 7 1/4" x 9"; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837
    Cambridge, (Mass.), 3pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The Mass. Hist. Soc. congratulates the A.P.S. upon the formation of the Historical and Literary Committee.
  - Joseph McKean to (Peter S.) DuPonceau, May 8, 1816; 7 5/16" x 9 3/16"; McKean, Joseph
    H(arvard) College, A.L.S. Will be pleased to promote the wishes of the Historical and Literary Committee of the A.P.S.
  - Report of Committee appointed on Mr. Spafford's paper respecting the treatment of iron ores, May 10, 1816; 8" x 10"; Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839
    A.D.S: Thomas Cooper, Jos. Cloud, William Hembel, jr. 1p.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 12, 1816; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Middleton, John, Izard, 1785-1849
    Washington Hall, A.L.S. 1p.,add.and end. Forwards dried plants requested by J.Vaughan for the APS.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 14, 1816; 8" x 10"; Norton, Andrews, 1786-1853
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Acknowledges volumes of APS Transactions for [Harvard] university.
  - Purchases of books and periodical for the A.P.S. Library, 1816 May 17- 1846 July; American Philosophical Society.
    Over 30 years of receipts for books and periodicals purchased for the A.P.S. Library (1816 May 17- 1846 July).
  - C(aesar) A. Rodney to ----, May 20, 1816; 8" x 13 1/8"; Rodney, C. A. (Caesar Augustus), 1772-1824
    Wilmington, 4pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. Will cooperate with work of Historical and Literary Committee to the A.P.S.
  - Report of the committee upon publication of [William] Byrd's journal., 1816 May 22; American Philosophical Society.
    Report of the committee on the publication of William Byrd's journal of the Virginia-Carolina border (May 22, 1816).
  - H. Steinhauer to Jno. Vaughan, May 23, 1816; 7 15/16" x 9 3/4"; Steinhauer, H.
    Bethlehem, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S.: [George Henry] Loskiel, History of the mission of the United Brethren among the Indians in North America.
  - P[eter] S. D[uPonceau] to John Vaughan, May 24, 1816; 8" x 10"; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.I. Arrangement of pamphlets in the A.P.S. library. European scholars and American Indian languages.
  - John Lardner to John Vaughan, May 24, 1816; 8 1/4" x 10"; Lardner, John
    Tacony, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S.: a letter from James Logan to the sons of William Penn, dated 1728.
  - Sam[ue]l Miller to John Vaughan, May 24, 1816; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Miller, Samuel
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S.: Medical repository, in fifteen volumes.
  - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson;], June 3, 1816; 12-1/2x8; Valli, Eusebio, 1762-1816
    A.L.S. 17p.and end. In Italian. Concerning yellow fever. Bur.of rolls; ser.2,vol.83,no.141. Enc.originally in letter from Valli to DuPonceau; June 28, 1816. FILM199 FRAME 722
  - W[illia]m Vaughan to John Vaughan, June 5, 1816; 7 11/16" x 9 13/16"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London, 1 p., address and endorsements. A.L.S. Forwards to the A.P.S.: Horticultural Society, Transactions, II, pt. 4.
  - Letter to [John] Vaughan, June 10, 1816; 10x8; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. In French. Forwards publications. Film 403 Frame 55
  - John Mason Good to the Secretary of the A.P.S., June 18, 1816; 7 3/8" x 9"; Good, John Mason, 1764-1827
    London, 4 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Inquires concerning lost parcels of books. Forwards several numbers of British Review to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to [the A.P.S.], June 19, 1816; 10x8; Milbert, Jacques Gérard, 1766-1840
    A.L.S. 1p., end. In French. Forwards volume.
  - Report of the committee charged with the communication of Dr. [Thomas] Cooper, relative to the blue iron ore, June 21, 1816; 7 15/16" x 9 7/8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 2 pp. and endorsement. D.S.: Zaccheus Collins, R[obert] M. Patterson. Publication in Transactions recommended.
  - Report of the committee appointed to inquire whether the Center Square house is suitable for an observatory, June 21, 1816; 7 5/8" x 8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: F. R. Hassler, R[obert] Patterson, R[obert] M. Patterson. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 464.
  - D. B. Warden to John Vaughan, June 22, 1816; 7 5/8" x 9 3/4"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Concerning various books sent to Mr. Short and to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to [Peter S.] DuPonceau, June 28, 1816; 12x7-1/2; Valli, Eusebio, 1762-1816
    Trenton, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In Italian. Enc. Concerning the translation of his article on yellow fever which he sent to Jefferson, for Wistar. For enc.,see: Valli to Jefferson; June 3, 1816. Film 199 Frame 712
  - W[illiam] Short to John Vaughan, July 3, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Short, William, 1759-1849
    Librarian of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, 1 p. and address. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S.: several volumes "more generally useful in the library of the Society than in mine."
  - Letter to [the A.P.S.], Philadelphia, July 8, 1816; 12x8; Geological Society of London
    London, L.S.: A. B. Granville. 1p. and add., end. Forwards publications.
  - Observatory committee of the A.P.S. to the Select and Common Councils of the city of Philadelphia, July 11, 1816; 8" x 13 1/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 3 pp. and endorsement. D.S.: Jno. Sergeant and four others. Petition for a grant of the use of the Center Square building as an astronomical observatory. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 465.
  - Horatio Gates Spafford to Peter S. DuPonceau, July 11, 1816; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Spafford, Horatio Gates, 1778-1832
    Albany, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Wishes to have his paper upon iron and steel returned to him. Sends to A.P.S. library: a copy of the Gazette of New York.
  - C(aspar) Wistar to J(ohn) Vaughan, July 15, 1816; 8 1/8" x 10"; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
    ----, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Inquires about certain designated books.
  - Letter to Benjamin Walter, Williamsburg, July 23, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 43.) Asks for documents for the committee.
  - Letter to [John G. E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, July 31, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 44.) Concerning the Indians of the U.S. and their languages.
  - W. J. Myddelton to John Vaughan, August 3, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Myddelton, W. J.
    Philadelphia, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. With regard to models of farm machinery deposited in A.P.S. room.
  - Letter to [John G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Aug. 5, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 46.) Concerning Indian linguistics.
  - W[illiam] Vaughan to John Vaughan, August 8, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 13/16"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Sends to the A.P.S.: Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society for 1816, part i.
  - Sketch of the plan of an ancient work, Aug. 31, 1816; 8" x 9 1/2"; Short, Charles Wilkins, 1794-1863
    three miles to the south-east of Lexington (Ky.). [] A. sketch S. 1p. End: C.W. Short. Aug. 31,1816. Lexington Ky. Description of a fort near Lexington Kentucky read 4 Oct. 1816. See Minutes of Oct. 4, 1816.
  - Report of committee on Lewis Kunitz' paper on leeches, Sept. 6, 1816; 4x 7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R.M.Patterson. 1p.and end.
  - Observatory committee of the A.P.S. to the committee of the Select and Common Councils of the city of Philadelphia, September 11, 1816; 8 1/4" x 9 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. D.S.: Peter S. DuPonceau and four others. Statement of grants requested in re Center Square observatory.
  - R[obert] M. Patterson to George Vaux, September 11, 1816; 7 3/8" x 9 5/8"; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    Philadelphia, 6 pp. L. Copy. In re anonymous letter concerning objections to use of Centre Square house as an astronomical observatory.
  - Letter to [the American philosophical society], Sept. 15, 1816; 9-1/2x8; L., A. F.
    A.L.S.with initials. 4p. In German. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 38.)
  - Letter to the A.P.S., Sept. 17, 1816; 10x8; Utzschneider, Joseph von, 1763-1840
    Bavaria, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Enc.of 2 printed sheets. In French. Sends prices of optical instruments. For enclosures, see: Broadsides,nos.362-3
  - Letter to J[ohn G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Sept. 19, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 4p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 49) Concerning Indian linguistics.
  - W(illiam) Barton to Peter S. DuPonceau, October 5, 1816; 7 1/4" x 12"; Barton, William, 1754-1817
    Lane(?), 3 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Personal letter. Reasons for present inability to contribute to Historical and Literary Committee of A.P.S.
  - [Joseph] Delaplaine to John Vaughan, October 11, 1816; 7 7/8" x 9 11/16"; Delaplaine, Joseph, 1777-1824
    [Philadelphia], 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L. in 3d. per. Presents to the A.P.S., a copy of his Repository of the lives... of distinguished American characters.
  - Letter to the president of the Philosophical society, Nov. 2, 1816; 8" x 10"; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817
    Eleutherian near Wilmington, Del., Photostat of A.Dr. of L. 1p. In French. ---- Photostat of second draft of same letter signed. 2p. and add. In French. Presents bust of Turgot by Houdon to the Society. Presented by Henry Francis du Pont, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to David B. Warden, Nov. 24, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Morris, Anthony, 1766-1860
    Geneva, Copy of L. 3p. Suggests an exchange of scientific information between the scientists of Switzerland and those of the United States, with Mr. Warden as the medium of exchange.
  - Letter to Rich[ar]d Rush, Nov. 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 54.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
  - Letter to du Pont de Nemours, Dec. 6, 1816; 8" x 9 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, Photostat of L.S: Tho. C. James, secretary. 1p. and add. Acknowledges bust of Turgot by Houdon. Presented by Henry Francis du Pont, Jan. 1945.
  - Report of committee on [Eugenius] Nulty's paper on a paper by Rittenhouse, Dec. 6, 1816; 4-1/2x5; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R.M. Patterson and John G. Biddle. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.467. Printed: Trans.,n.s.,vol.I, 395 ff. FILM 403 FRAME 163
  - Daniel Brent to [Peter S.] DuPonceau, December 16, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Brent, Daniel, 1774-1841
    Department of State, [Washington], 2 pp. A.L.S. Has set apart for the A.P.S. a copy of the new edition of the Laws of the United States, and a set of congressional documents.
  - Richard Rush to P[eter] S. DuPonceau, December 16, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859
    Washington, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. A complete set of the new edition of the Laws of the United States to be set apart for the A.P.S.
  - Letter to the president of the Philosophical, Dec. 18, 1816; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Ramirez, Alexander, 1777-1821
    Havanna, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Sends eulogium on Dr. [Eusebio] Valli who died of yellow fever. The Royal society of Havana has erected a monument in his honor. Cf. Minutes Feb. 21, 1817.
  - Letter to du Pont de Nemours, Dec. 23, 1816; 8" x 9 3/4"; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Philadelphia, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Encloses acknowledgment from the Society for the bust of Turgot by Houdon. Presented by Henry Francis du Pont, Jan. 1945.
  - Jared Mansfield to John Vaughan, December 28, 1816; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Mansfield, Jared, 1759-1830
    West Point, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Due to pressure of work finds it imposible to prepare "any thing worthy of publication" for the A.P.S.
  - List of books purchased by John Vaughan, 1816; 9x6; John Conrad & Co.
    D.S.: A.B.Murray. 1p.and end.
  - An ordinance granting to the American Philosophical Society the use of certain parts of the public building in the centre square for the purpose of an astronomical observatory, 1816(?); 7 1/4" x 9 5/8"; Philadelphia (Pa.). City Council
    [Philadelphia], ----, 2 pp. and endorsement. Dr.D.
  - Papers pertaining to the purchase of fuels, Feb. 10, Sept. 29, 1816, 1847; American Philosophical Society
    D. 66 items. Various sizes. Includes coal, coke, and wood.
  - List of members of the American Philosophical Society elected since 1809, January, 1817; 9 5/8" x 14 5/8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement.
  - Report of committee appointed to receive proposals for the lease of the rooms not occupied by the society, , 1817; 12-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    [ca.]. D.S: J[oh]n Vaughan and R[ober]t Patterson. 1p. Refers to Thomas Cooper and Thomas Sully.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, March, 1817; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Smith, J. A.
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. Lends a history of Pennsylvania to the APS, sending the same in the care of Mr. Barker.
  - Isaiah Thomas to Thomas T. Hewson, January 8, 1817; 8" x 10"; Thomas, Isaiah, 1749-1831
    Corresponding Secretary of the A.P.S., Worcester, Mass., 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges his election to membership in the American Philosophical Society.
  - Isaiah Thomas to John Vaughan, January 8, 1817; 8" x 10"; Thomas, Isaiah, 1749-1831
    Treasurer of the A.P.S., Worcester, Mass., 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledge receipt of certificate of membership in the American Philosophical Society.
  - Abiel Holmes to Peter S. DuPonceau, January 13, 1817; 8 1/4" x 10"; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837
    Cambridge, (Mass.), 3pp., address and endorsement, A.L.S. Returns thanks for election to A.P.S. Prince collection acquired by the Massachusetts Historical society.
  - Abiel Holmes to Thomas T. Hewson, January 13, 1817; 8" x 10"; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837
    Cambridge, [Mass.], 1 p. and endorsement. Acknowledges his election to membership in the American Philosophical Society.
  - A[biel] Holmes to John Vaughan, January 14, 1817; 8 1/4" x 9 15/16"; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837
    Cambridge, [Mass.], 1 p., address and endorsements. A.L.S. Has paid admission fee required of new members of the American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to Prof. Pictet, Jan. 20, 1817; 8" x 10"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, Copy of L.S. 1p. and add. Addressed to the Secretary of the American philosophical society. Is pleased to act as the channel for the exchange of scientific and literary correspondence between Geneva and the United States.
  - Richard Rush to P[eter] S. DuPonceau, January 22, 1817; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859
    Washington, 1p. A.L.S. Acknowledges his election to membership in the American Philosophical Society.
  - Sam[ue]l Ewing and Geo[rge] Vaux to the A.P.S., January 24, 1817; 6 5/8" x 81/8"; Ewing, Samuel
    Athenaeum, [Philadelphia], 2 pp., address and endorsement. L.S. Application, in name of Athenaeum, for rental of rooms in Philosophical Hall "at present occupied by Mr. Sully."
  - A[biel] Holmes to [Peter S.] DuPonceau, January 31, 1817; 7 3/4" x 9 13/16"; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837
    Cambridge, [Mass.], 1 p. A.L.S. Sends to the A.P.S.: Massachusetts Historical Society, Collections, X.
  - List of members elected since 1809, 1817 January; American Philosophical Society.
    A list of A.P.S. members elected since 1809, including their location and the month and year of their election.
  - D. B. Warden to Tho[ma]s C. James, February 1, 1817; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Secretary of the A.P.S., Paris, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Encloses a letter to Professor Pictet of Geneva, concerning the exchange of publications between the A.P.S. and European learned societies.
  - The committee of the Athenaeum to the committee of the American Philosophical Society, Feb. 6, 1817; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Athenaeum of Philadelphia